<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: meta | Erik Cunningham (@trinary)]]></title>
  <link href="http://trinary.github.com/blog/categories/meta/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://trinary.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-07-14T17:34:13-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://trinary.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erik Cunningham]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting This Set Up...Again]]></title>
    <link href="http://trinary.github.com/blog/2012/07/14/getting-this-set-up-dot-dot-dot-again/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-14T18:38:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://trinary.github.com/blog/2012/07/14/getting-this-set-up-dot-dot-dot-again</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4>Hello there!</h4>

<p>Once again I'm trying to get in the habit of writing.  I think the only way I'm going to be able to do it is to just start and not worry too much if what I'm writing is particularly groundbreaking.</p>

<h2>Information Display</h2>

<p>I'd like to start with one of my favorite subjects: information visualization and clarity of display.</p>

<p>I was recently asked to implement a "dial" style representation of a single data point for a dashboard system I'm working on.  I think I managed to create something that looks ok, but I don't think it's a good way to display a single piece of information.  Let's discuss why.</p>

<h3>What's a Dial?</h3>

<p>By "dial", I mean a speedometer-type representation of a value.  You have a circular layout, typically with an indicator pointing from the center to a particular spot on the circle.  By rotating clockwise, the indicator shows an increase in magnitude.</p>

<h3>Why don't I like them?</h3>

<p>Dials, because of their round nature, take up a ton of space.  For that budget of display area the viewer gets only a single point of information.  It's difficult to represent any context without making things cluttered.  You can add a reference point (e.g. a historical average), but doing so with another indicator will make it look like a clock and require a legend, using a simple dot on the circumference of the dial increases the radius of the whole visualization, and so on.</p>

<p>Furthermore, they are difficult to compare to one another when several are used together.  The indicators for totally different values can be at the same plane, think 9 o'clock vs 3 o'clock on a line of clocks next to each other.</p>

<p>Perhaps most importantly, they don't use any of the typical visual indicators that our brains have been trained to associate with magnitude for a zillion years.  Bar charts are instantly parseable, because we implicitly understand that increased area = increased value.  Distance from a baseline in the case of line or area charts are similarly simple to interpret as enclosing greater area as magnitude increases.  Angular distance from an arbitrary point is a recently invented way to communicate magnitude, and one that is difficult to interpret by comparison.</p>

<h3>What should you use instead?</h3>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bullet_graph">Stephen Few's Bullet graphs</a> are an ideal alternative to the dial.  Here's what you get by using them:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>A magnitude representation that makes instant sense to the brain (length)</p></li>
<li><p>Ranges for status context that cost very little ink and space</p></li>
<li><p>An additional indicator for historical context that can be easily understood and compared</p></li>
<li><p>Easily scannable and comparable lists of charts</p></li>
<li><p>A layout that makes labels and current value displays easy to add in a pleasing way.<br/>
For example, if you have long labels you can stack multiple bullets vertically and not force your label text to wrap awkwardly or have to space them too far apart.</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>What's next?</h3>

<p>I'm continuing to work on data visualization, I think it's the most fun I've had coding in a long time.  I'm working (quite infrequently) on a system that uses websockets to let browsers subscribe to data from various sources, and when I can I'll add some quality displays of data.</p>

<p>On friday I get to go see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Tufte">Edward Tufte</a> give one of his all-day seminars on data visualization!  I cannot wait, I've been wanting to attend one for years and years.  I'll definitely be writing about the class.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
